<requirements>
  <background>
    Currently commissioned arts are organized by folders

    ```
    .
    ├── Chibi
    │ ├── chibi-background-banzhishouza.jpg
    │ ├── chibi-banzhishouza.png
    │ ├── chibi-gengzi-1.png
    │ ├── chibi-gengzi-2.png
    │ ├── chibi-with-dileselon.png
    │ ├── qrcode.png
    │ ├── qrcode.psd
    │ └── qrcode.sai2
    ├── Other
    │ ├── cut-tail.png
    │ ├── totem.png
    │ ├── weapon-greatsword-watermark.jpg
    │ ├── weapon-greatsword.png
    │ └── ...
    ├── Monochrome
    │ └── ...
    └── ...
    ```

    As the number of commission art grows, the following problems have emerged
    1. An image may belong to multiple categories
    An avatar may be both an avatar and monochrome
    Since the filesystem is tree-structured, an image can only belong to one category folder, which
    is
    clearly unreasonable
    2. Titles contain irrelevant information
    Some metadata is mixed into titles, such as whether it has a background, the artist,
    co-commission
    partner, etc.
    Metadata needs to be preserved, but mixing it into titles reduces title readability
    3. An image may exist in multiple formats
    4. The way images are added, managed, and previewed is quite primitive
    A better method for managing commission art is needed, including
    - Adding and deleting
    - Metadata
    - Multi-dimensional filtering and categorization
    - Preview
    - Different resolution export
    - \[Optional\] Extract `psd` layers for export
    - \[Optional\] Physical watermark / digital watermark
    - \[Optional\] CLIP - `image2txt` image accessibility
    - \[Optional\] Safe mode
  </background>

  <reference>
    [Project
    link](https://ryuhane.notion.site/8cc55c3a72c94832983b36bc514a8f7b?v=a4b1ded8480d458297966e7fc3349f02)
    Notion-based commission management
    Consists of two parts: settings and commissions. Settings include characters, outfits, weapons,
    etc. Commissions support preview, search, filtering, and sorting
</reference>

  <goals>
    Implement a commission management application that meets Heiyao's needs
    The core is commission art management; settings and commission inspiration are currently managed
    with Obsidian and that is sufficient

    Features to implement
    - Images, metadata
    - Preview, export
    - Search, filter, sort
    - Authentication for edit access
</goals>

  <design>
    <entities>
      <metadata>
        Title
        Description
        Time - the completion time of the commission, precise to the day
        Labels - multi-select, unified label system covering categories, tags, and rating:
        - Category - predefined labels for image type, e.g. Chibi, Avatar, etc.
        - Tag - freely defined labels
        - Rating - exactly one required per commission; predefined values: General, Mature, Adult
        - Label types differ only in frontend display semantics; the backend stores all labels
        identically
        Characters - multi-select, see Characters
        Artists - multi-select, see Artists
        Cover image - small image
        Files - a commission contains nodes, each node contains files. Files may be any format:
        rendered images (png, jpg), source files (psd, sai2), design documents, etc.
        - Each file has a format, an optional label (e.g. "with background", "差分 A"), and a flag
        indicating whether it is a displayable image
        - Displayable image files additionally store resolution (width × height) and a focal point
        for
        thumbnail cropping
        - Only displayable image files are eligible to be used as cover art
      </metadata>

      <character>
        Name - the character's name; kept as a first-class field to support DB-level search and
        filtering
        Settings - an XML blob for all other character attributes (species, appearance, lore, etc.);
        parsed by the frontend
        Note: species filtering (see Search, Filter, Sort) is expected to operate on the parsed XML
        at
        the application layer, not the DB layer
      </character>

      <artist>
        Name - the artist's name; kept as a first-class field to support DB-level search and
        filtering
        Info - an XML blob for all other artist attributes (contact links, social handles, notes,
        etc.); parsed by the frontend
      </artist>

      <lifecycle>
        A commission progresses through a series of stages tracked as ordered nodes. Admins can
        freely
        define and reorder nodes.

        Nodes are linear and sequential. Each node has:
        - Name - the stage name, e.g. "Sketching", "Lineart", "Delivered"
        - Order - explicit integer position to preserve admin-defined ordering
        - Started at - timestamp recording when this stage began
        - Files - any files received at this stage (rendered images, source files, design docs,
        etc.)
        Each commission also has exactly one system-managed **detached node**:
        - Automatically created when the commission is created; cannot be deleted or reordered
        - When a regular node is deleted, all its associated images are reassigned to the detached
        node
        - Images in the detached node are considered uncategorized and should be visually
        distinguished in the UI

        Commission-level lifecycle fields (stored on commission_metadata):
        - Confirmed at - timestamp when the commission was accepted/confirmed by the admin
        - Price amount - the agreed commission price as a decimal
        - Price currency - ISO 4217 currency code, e.g. "USD", "JPY", "CNY"
      </lifecycle>
    </entities>

    <storage>
      All commission metadata is stored uniformly in a single database.
      Image files are managed through an abstracted storage layer that decouples the database from
      any
      specific storage backend.
      - The initial supported backend is the local filesystem
      - The design must allow future backends (e.g. S3, GCS) to be added without schema changes
      - Each image file is represented as a storage object with a backend type, an optional
      container/bucket, and a backend-specific key
      - The concept of a "commission folder" is a convention of the local backend, not a
      database-level constraint
</storage>

    <export> Both export modes are privileged operations that require edit access. Two export modes
      are supported. <database-export>
        Used when migrating between database or application installations.
        - No physical files are exported
        - Exports the full database contents (commissions, metadata, nodes, labels, characters,
      artists,
        storage object records, etc.)
        - Storage object records retain their original backend type, bucket, and key, so files
      remain
        resolvable after the DB is imported into a new installation provided the storage backend is
      accessible at the same location
        - Intended for full application migration, not for end-user file delivery
      </database-export>

    <file-export>
      Exports physical files packaged as a `.zip` archive, prompted for download once the archive is
      ready.
        - Directory layout inside the zip: `{commission_artists}-{commission_id}/{node_name}/`
        - `commission_artists` is derived from the names of all artists linked to the commission,
      e.g.
        `artistA-artistB-42`
        - Each node becomes a subdirectory named after the node; the detached node is included if it
      contains files
        - File timestamps:
        - The commission directory's creation time is set to the date of the most recently started
      node
        (`started_at`)
        - Each node directory's creation time is set to that node's `started_at` date
        - Only physical files are exported; no metadata files are generated
      </file-export>
    </export>

    <ux-and-ui>
      <pages> 
        Pages Should mainly include: home page, add/edit page, detail page 
          
        <home-page>
          The home page is similar to a photo album app design, mainly used to display the
        commission
          list
          - Can add a commission -> navigates to the add commission page
          - Can operate on a commission
          - Can select multiple commissions for batch operations
          - Can click a commission -> navigates to the commission detail page
          - Can filter, search, and sort to change the currently displayed commission list
        </home-page>

        <detail-page>
        Mainly used to display commission details
          - Display commission full-size image
          - Display commission metadata
          - Can operate on the commission
          - Can edit or delete the commission -> edit navigates to the edit page, delete navigates
        to
          the home page
        </detail-page>

        <add-edit-page>
        Similar to the detail page
          - Can add or remove commission full-size images
          - Can edit commission metadata
          - Can cancel or complete -> navigates to the parent page
          - Should validate data validity
        </add-edit-page>
      </pages>

      <image-layout> 
        The image layout leans toward referencing [FurAffinity](https://www.furaffinity.net) 
        
        <standard-layout>
          All images have the same width and height. Reference: [Natsume Ryuhane](#natsume-ryuhane)
        Pros
          - Clean and uniform layout
          Cons
          - Thumbnails of extreme aspect ratio images will be heavily cropped
        </standard-layout>

        <waterfall-layout>
          Multi-row or multi-column layout; each row has equal height or each column has equal width,
          extending infinitely in one direction. Reference: [Pinterest](https://www.pinterest.com)
          Pros
          - Adapts to images of various sizes without cropping
          - High space utilization

          Cons
          - Displayed images are unordered
          - Portrait images in a horizontal layout or landscape images in a vertical layout will
        appear
          smaller
          - May lose the focal point during preview
        </waterfall-layout>

      <custom-layout>
        Manually adjust the size and position of each image based on importance, dimensions, etc.,
        achieving a photo wall-like effect
          Pros
          - Carefully designed layout with good visual effect

          Cons
          - Displayed images are unordered
          - Only suitable for a limited number of images; cannot add, delete, or reorder without
        re-laying out
        </custom-layout>

      <FurAffinity>
        1. The layout flows left-to-right, top-to-bottom -> preserves order
          2. Equal spacing between images; all images within a column have equal height -> the
        trade-off
          is that each column's height fluctuates within a certain range
        </FurAffinity>
      </image-layout>

      <search-filter-sort> Whether searching, filtering, or sorting, all operate on a proper subset
        of all commissions <search>
          Search filters the full set of commissions
          Search can be exact or fuzzy

          Search types
          - Search by title
          - Search by description
          - \[Optional\] Search by image content

          Search can target a single type or multiple types
        </search>

      <filter>
        Filter operates on the full set of commissions or on search results
          Filtering is exact

          Filter types
          - Filter by category - categories are searchable
          - Filter by tag - tags are searchable
          - Filter by rating
          - Filter by time range
          - Filter by character count range
          - Filter by character species - species are searchable
          - Filter by character or artist name - names are searchable
          - Filter by image format

          Filter types can be stacked, and within a specific type multiple values can be selected,
        e.g.
          filter by multiple tags
        </filter>

      <sort>
        Sort determines the display order of commissions

          Sort has ascending and descending
          Sort has two dimensions
          - By commission completion time
          - By commission title alphabetical order - needs to account for pinyin
        </sort>
      </search-filter-sort>

      <other>
        <thumbnails>
          Should allow users to specify the main subject area of an image to generate correct
          thumbnails, ensuring proper cropping
        </thumbnails>

        <catrgories-and-tags>
          Categories and tags should only differ semantically, not in implementation
        </catrgories-and-tags>
      </other>
    </ux-and-ui>
  </design>
</requirements>